Chapter 2 Leaving Gateshead
第二章 离开盖茨黑德
I woke up to find the doctor lifting me very carefully into my own bed.
我醒来时发现医生小心翼翼地将我放回自己的床上。
It was good to be back in my familiar bedroom, with a warm fire and candlelight.
回到熟悉的卧室真好，房间里有温暖的火炉和烛光。
It was also a great relief to recognise Dr Lloyd, who Mrs Reed called in for her servants.
认出是劳埃德医生来照顾我，也让我松了一口气，里德夫人总是叫他来看仆人。
She always called a specialist for herself and the children.
她自己和孩子们生病时，总是请专科医生。
He was looking after me so kindly, I felt he would protect me from Mrs Reed.
他如此善待我，我觉得他会保护我不受里德夫人的伤害。
He talked to me a little, then gave Bessie orders to take good care of me.
他跟我聊了几句，然后吩咐贝茜好好照顾我。
When he left, I felt very lonely again.
他走后，我再次感到孤独。
But I was surprised to find that Bessie did not scold me at all.
但令我惊讶的是，贝茜没有责骂我。
In fact, she was so kind to me that I became brave enough to ask a question.
事实上，她对我非常亲切，这让我鼓起勇气问了一个问题。
Bessie, what's happened? Am I ill?
贝茜，发生了什么事？我病了吗？
Yes, you became ill in the bedroom, but you'll get better, don't worry Miss Jane, she answered.
“是的，你在卧室里病了，但你会好起来的，别担心简小姐，”她回答道。
Then she went next door to fetch another servant. I could hear her whispers.
然后她去了隔壁房间找另一个仆人。我能听到她的低语声。
Sarah, come in here and sleep with me and that poor child tonight.
“莎拉，今晚进来和我一起睡，还有那可怜的孩子。”
I don't stay alone with her, she might die.
“我不敢和她单独呆着，她可能会死的。”
She was so ill last night. Do you think she saw a ghost?
“她昨晚病得很重。你认为她见鬼了吗？”
Mrs Reed was too hard on her, I think.
“我觉得里德夫人对她太苛刻了。”
So the two servants slept in my room while I lay awake all night, trembling with fear and eyes wide open in horror, imagining ghosts in every corner.
于是两个仆人在我的房间里睡觉，而我整晚都醒着，吓得瑟瑟发抖，眼睛睁得大大的，恐惧地想象着每个角落都有鬼魂。
Fortunately, I suffered no serious illness as a result of my terrible experience in the red room, although I shall never forget that night.
幸运的是，我在红房间的可怕经历没有导致我生病，尽管我永远不会忘记那个夜晚。
But the shock left me nervous and depressed for the next few days.
但那次的惊吓让我在接下来的几天里感到紧张和沮丧。
I cried all day long, and although Bessie tried hard to tempt me with nice things to eat or my favourite books, I took no pleasure in eating or even in reading.
我整天都在哭泣，尽管贝茜努力用好吃的食物或我最喜欢的书来诱惑我，但我对吃东西甚至读书都不感兴趣。
I knew I had no one to love me and nothing to look forward to.
我知道没有人爱我，也没有什么值得期待的。
When the doctor came again, he seemed a little surprised to find me looking so miserable.
医生再次来的时候，发现我看起来如此悲伤，他似乎有些惊讶。
Perhaps she's crying because she couldn't go out with Mrs Reed in the carriage this morning, suggested Bessie.
“也许她因为今天早上没能和里德夫人一起乘马车出门而哭泣，”贝茜建议道。
Surely she's more sensible than that, said the doctor, smiling at me. She's a big girl now.
“她肯定比那更明智，”医生笑着看着我说。“她现在已经是大姑娘了。”
I'm not crying about that. I hate going out in the carriage, I said quickly. I'm crying because I'm miserable.
“我不是因为那个哭泣。我讨厌坐马车出去，”我立刻说道。“我哭是因为我很悲惨。”
Oh, really, miss, said Bessie.
“哦，真的，小姐，”贝茜说道。
The doctor looked at me thoughtfully. He had small, grey, intelligent eyes.
医生若有所思地看着我。他有一双小而灰的聪明眼睛。
Just then a bell rang for the servants' dinner.
就在这时，仆人们的晚餐铃响了。
You can go, Bessie, he said. I'll stay here talking to Miss Jane till you come back.
“你可以走了，贝茜，”他说。“我会在这里和简小姐聊天，直到你回来。”
After Bessie had left, he asked,
贝茜离开后，他问道，
What really made you ill?
“究竟是什么让你生病的？”
I was locked up in a room with a ghost in the dark.
“我被锁在一个有鬼的房间里，还关着灯。”
Afraid of ghosts, are you? he smiled.
“你怕鬼吗？”他笑道。
Of Mr Reed's ghost, yes. He died in that room, you know.
“怕里德先生的鬼，是的。你知道他死在那个房间里。”
Nobody even goes in there anymore.
“现在没有人再进那个房间了。”
It was cruel to lock me in there alone without a candle. I shall never forget it.
“把我一个人锁在那里，没有蜡烛，太残忍了。我永远不会忘记那件事。”
But you aren't afraid now.
“但你现在不怕了。”
There must be another reason why you're so sad, he said, looking kindly at me.
“肯定还有其他原因让你如此悲伤，”他说，善意地看着我。
How could I tell him all the reasons for my unhappiness?
“我怎么能告诉他我所有的不幸原因呢？”
I have no father or mother, brothers or sisters, I began.
“我没有父亲或母亲，没有兄弟或姐妹，”我开始说。
But you have a kind aunt and cousins.
“但你有一个善良的姨妈和表兄弟姐妹。”
But John Reed knocked me down and my aunt locked me in the red room, I cried.
“但约翰·里德打倒了我，我的姨妈把我关在红房间里，”我哭道。
There was a pause.
沉默了一会儿。
Don't you like living at Gateshead in such a beautiful house? he asked.
“你不喜欢住在盖茨黑德这么漂亮的房子里吗？”他问道。
I would be glad to leave it, but I have nowhere else to go.
“我很想离开这里，但我没有其他地方可去。”
You have no relations apart from Mrs Reed?
“除了里德夫人，你没有其他亲戚吗？”
I think I may have some who are very poor, but I know nothing about them, I answered.
“我想我可能有一些非常穷的亲戚，但我对他们一无所知，”我回答道。
Would you like to go to school? he asked finally.
“你愿意去上学吗？”他最后问道。
I thought for a moment.
我想了想。
I knew very little about school, but at least it would be a change, the start of a new life.
我对学校了解不多，但至少这会是一个改变，一个新生活的开始。
Yes, I would like to go, I replied in the end.
“是的，我愿意去，”我最终答道。
Well, well, said the doctor to himself as he got up, we'll see.
“好吧，好吧，”医生自言自语道，他起身走了，“孩子娇弱，她应该换个环境。”
A child is delicate, she ought to have a change of air.
孩子体弱，她应该换个环境。
I heard later from the servants that he had spoken to Mrs Reed about me and that she had agreed immediately to send me to school.
后来我从仆人们那里听说，他曾与里德夫人谈论过我，她立刻同意送我去上学。
Abbott said Mrs Reed would be glad to get rid of me.
阿博特说里德夫人很高兴能摆脱我。
In this conversation, I also learned for the first time that my father had been a poor vicar.
在这次对话中，我第一次知道我的父亲曾是个贫穷的牧师。
When he married my mother, Miss Jane Reed of Gateshead, the Reed family were so angry that they disinherited her.
当他与我母亲结婚时，我母亲是盖茨黑德的简·里德小姐，里德家族非常愤怒，把她遗弃了。
I also heard that my parents both died of an illness only a year after their wedding.
我还听说，我的父母在婚后一年因病去世了。
But days and weeks passed, and Mrs Reed still said nothing about sending me to school.
但日子一天天过去，里德夫人仍然没有提到送我去上学的事。
One day, as she was scolding me, I suddenly threw a question at her.
有一天，当她在责骂我时，我突然问了她一个问题。
The words just came out without my planning to say them.
这些话是在我没有计划好要说的时候说出来的。
What would Uncle Reed say to you if he were alive, I asked.
“如果叔叔·里德还活着，他会对你说什么？”我问道。
What, cried Mrs Reed, her cold grey eyes full of fear, staring at me as if I were a ghost.
“什么！”里德夫人叫道，她那冷灰色的眼睛充满恐惧，像看到鬼一样盯着我。
I had to continue.
“我必须继续说下去。”
My Uncle Reed is now in heaven and can see all you think and do, and so can my parents.
“我的叔叔里德现在在天堂，可以看到你所有的想法和行为，我的父母也是。”
They know how you hate me and are cruel to me.
“他们知道你是多么讨厌我，对我多么残忍。”
Mrs Reed smacked my face and left me without a word.
里德夫人打了我的脸，什么话也没说就离开了我。
I was scolded for an hour by Bessie as the most ungrateful child in the world.
贝茜责骂了我一个小时，说我是世界上最忘恩负义的孩子。
And indeed, with so much hate in my heart, I did feel wicked.
的确，我心中充满仇恨，确实感到自己很邪恶。
Christmas passed by, with no presents or new clothes for me.
圣诞节过去了，我没有收到礼物，也没有新衣服。
Every evening I watched Eliza and Georgiana putting on their new dresses and going out to parties.
每天晚上我看着伊丽莎和乔治安娜穿上她们的新衣服，去参加派对。
Sometimes Bessie would come up to me in my lonely bedroom, bringing a piece of cake.
有时贝茜会在我孤独的卧室里给我带来一块蛋糕。
Sometimes she would tell me a story, and sometimes she would kiss me goodnight.
有时她会给我讲个故事，有时她会亲我一口，说晚安。
When she was kind to me, I thought she was the best person in the world, but she did not always have time for me.
她对我好的时候，我觉得她是世界上最好的人，但她并不总是有时间照顾我。
On the morning of the 15th of January, Bessie rushed up to my room to tell me a visitor wanted to see me.
1月15日上午，贝茜急忙跑到我的房间告诉我，有客人想见我。
Who could it be? I knew Mrs Reed would be there too, and I was frightened of seeing her again.
会是谁呢？我知道里德夫人也会在场，我害怕再见到她。
When I nervously entered the breakfast room, I looked up at a black column.
当我紧张地走进早餐室时，我抬头看到了一个黑色的柱子。
At least that was what he looked like to me.
至少在我看来，他看起来像是一个黑色的柱子。
He was a tall, thin man dressed all in black, with a cold, stony face at the top of the column.
他是一个高大、瘦削的男人，身穿黑色衣服，柱子顶端是冰冷、坚硬的面孔。
This is the little girl I wrote to you about, said Mrs Reed to the stony stranger.
“这是我写信给你提到的小女孩，”里德夫人对那位冰冷的陌生人说道。
Well, Jane Eyre, said the stranger heavily, and are you a good child?
“嗯，简·爱，”那位陌生人沉重地说道，“你是个好孩子吗？”
It was impossible to say yes with Mrs Reed sitting there, so I was silent.
“在里德夫人坐在那里时，我不可能说‘是’，所以我沉默不语。”
Perhaps the less said about that the better, Mr Brocklehurst, said Mrs Reed, shaking her head.
“也许最好少说些，布洛克赫斯特先生，”里德夫人摇头说道。
I'm sorry to hear it, he answered.
“我很遗憾听到这些，”他回答道。
Come here, Jane Eyre, and answer my questions.
“过来，简·爱，回答我的问题。”
Where do the wicked go after death?
“坏人死后去哪里？”
They go to hell, I answered.
“他们下地狱，”我回答道。
And what must you do to avoid going there? he asked.
“那你必须做什么才能避免去那里？”他问道。
I thought for a moment, but could not find the right answer.
我想了一会儿，但找不到正确的答案。
I must keep in good health and not die, I replied.
“我必须保持健康，不要死去，”我回答道。
Wrong! Children younger than you die all the time.
“错了！比你小的孩子经常死去。”
Another question. Do you enjoy reading the Bible?
“另一个问题。你喜欢读《圣经》吗？”
Yes, sometimes, I replied, hesitating.
“有时喜欢，”我犹豫地回答道。
That is not enough.
“这还不够。”
Your answers show me you have a wicked heart.
“你的回答告诉我你有一颗邪恶的心。”
You must pray to God to change it if you ever want to go to heaven.
“如果你想上天堂，必须向上帝祈求改变它。”
Mr Brocklehurst, interrupted Mrs Reed,
“布洛克赫斯特先生，”里德夫人打断道，
Mr Brocklehurst, interrupted Mrs Reed, I mentioned to you in my letter that this little girl has in fact a very bad character.
“布洛克赫斯特先生，”里德夫人打断道，“我在信中提到，这个小女孩其实性格很差。”
If you accept her at Lowood School, please make sure that the headmistress and teachers know how dishonest she is.
“如果你接纳她到洛伍德学校，请确保校长和老师们知道她是多么不诚实。”
She will try to lie to them, of course.
“她当然会试图欺骗他们。”
You see, Jane, you cannot try your tricks on Mr Brocklehurst.
“你看，简，你不能对布洛克赫斯特先生耍花招。”
However hard I had tried to please Mrs Reed in the past, she always thought the worst of me.
“无论我过去多么努力取悦里德夫人，她总是对我抱有最坏的想法。”
It was not surprising that I had come to hate her.
“我讨厌她也就不足为奇了。”
Now she was accusing me in front of a stranger.
“现在她在陌生人面前指责我。”
My hopes of starting a new life at school began to fade.
“我开始在学校开启新生活的希望开始消退。”
Do not worry, madam, Mr Brocklehurst said.
“别担心，夫人，”布洛克赫斯特先生说。
The teachers will watch her carefully.
“老师们会仔细看着她。”
Life at Lowood will do her good.
“洛伍德的生活对她有好处。”
We believe in hard work, plain food, simple clothes and no luxury of any kind.
“我们相信努力工作、简单的食物、简朴的衣服和没有任何奢侈品。”
I will send her as soon as possible then, Mr Brocklehurst.
“那么我会尽快送她去，布洛克赫斯特先生。”
I hope she will be taught according to her low position in life.
“我希望她能按照她卑微的地位受到教育。”
Indeed she will, madam.
“她一定会的，夫人。”
I hope she will be grateful for this opportunity to improve her character.
“我希望她能感激这个改善性格的机会。”
Little girl, read this book.
“小女孩，读这本书。”
It tells the story of the sudden death of a young girl who was a liar.
“它讲述了一个爱撒谎的小女孩突然去世的故事。”
Read and pray.
“读书并祈祷吧。”
After Mr Brocklehurst had given me the book and left, I felt I had to speak.
“布洛克赫斯特先生给我书后离开了，我感到必须说些什么。”
Anger was boiling up inside me.
“愤怒在我心中沸腾。”
I walked up to Mrs Reed and looked straight into her eyes.
“我走到里德夫人面前，直视她的眼睛。”
I do not deceive people.
“我不欺骗人。”
If I told lies, I would say I loved you. But I don't. I hate you.
“如果我撒谎，我会说我爱你。但我不爱你。我恨你。”
I will never call you aunt again as long as I live.
“我活着一天就永远不会再叫你姨妈。”
If anyone asks how you treated me, I will tell them the truth, that you are very cruel to me.
“如果有人问你怎么对我的，我会告诉他们实话，说你对我很残忍。”
People think you're a good woman, but you are lying to them.
“人们以为你是个好女人，但你在骗他们。”
Even before I'd finished, I began to experience a great feeling of freedom and relief.
“还没等我说完，我就开始感到一种巨大的自由和解脱感。”
At last I had said what I felt.
“终于我说出了自己的感受。”
Mrs Reed looked frightened and unhappy.
“里德夫人看起来害怕且不开心。”
Jane, I want to be your friend. You don't know what you're saying. You are too excited. Go to your room and lie down.
“简，我想成为你的朋友。你不知道自己在说什么。你太激动了。去你的房间躺下吧。”
I won't lie down. I'm quite calm. Send me to school soon, Mrs Reed. I hate living here.
“我不会躺下。我很冷静。快送我去上学吧，里德夫人。我讨厌住在这里。”
I will indeed send her soon, murmured Mrs Reed to herself.
“我确实会很快送她去，”里德夫人自言自语道。